Guide to the Slater Family collection circa 1850-2010
Oregon Historical Society, Research Library
Slater Family Collection
ca. 1850-2010
Oregon Historical Society, Davies Family Research Library Research Library 1200 SW Park Avenue Portland, Oregon 97205 Phone: 503-306-5240 Fax: 503-219-2040 E-mail: libreference@ohs.org
Coll 206
Slater Family
.9 linear feet 2 boxes
Family history, photographic images, books, newspaper clippings, and ephemera of the descendants of Oregon pioneers James H. Slater and Edna Elizabeth Gray. Includes travel photographs from Oregon, Canada, and the western U.S., and photographs of the 1962 Columbus Day storm in Portland, Oregon.
Historical Note
Bertha Slater Smith, native of Oregon, was best known as penning the Portland Rose Festival Rosarian’s slogan “For you a rose in Portland grows,” after winning a slogan contest in the early 1900s. Born in La Grande, Oregon, she was the daughter of pioneer parents. Her father, James H. Slater, came to Oregon by way of California in 1850. He was elected Prosecuting Attorney for the 5th Judicial District in 1866, served in the U.S. Congress from 1871-1873, and was a U.S. Senator from Oregon from 1879-1885. Bertha's mother, Edna Elizabeth Gray Slater, was born in Tennessee and was part of the storied “Lost Wagon Train” that first crossed the Cascade range at McKenzie Pass in 1853. Bertha graduated from the University of Oregon and served as president of the Sons and Daughters of the American Revolution. Her husband, Elmer Elwood Smith, was a descendent of another pioneer family whose ancestors fought in the American revolution.
The collection consists mostly of photographs dating from approximately 1850-1920. These include portraits, group photos, early snapshots, five tintype portraits, and many travel photographs, including a few battleships. Also included is a small photograph album documenting an auto trip to northeastern Oregon in 1914; negatives of scenic images; five Masonic code books; one file of newspaper clippings about the Oregon Zoo; loose album pages from the 1960s with images of the 1962 Columbus Day storm in Portland; and two pieces of school ephemera. Few of the portraits are identified. A number of images are of travel throughout the U.S. and parts of Canada, and many provide excellent images of North American cities and towns in the early part of the 20th century, including Montreal and the Louisiana Purchase Exposition of 1904 in St. Louis.
The collection is arranged in the following series:
Series A: Family History
Series B: Photographs
Series C: News clippings
Series D: Books and ephemera
The collection is open to the public.
Papers of James H. Slater are held by the Oregon Historical Society Research Library and designated Mss 2347.
The collection was assembled by Caroline Ruhmshottel, granddaughter of Bertha Slater Smith.
Acquired December 2010, Library Accession 27214.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Ruhmshottel, Caroline.; Smith, Bertha Slater--Archives.; Slater, Edna Elizabeth Gray.; Slater, Jas. H. (James Harvey), 1826-1899--Photographs.
Slater family--Photographs.
Louisiana Purchase Exposition (1904: Saint Louis, Mo.)--Photographs
Montréal (Québec)--Photographs
Floods--Oregon--Portland--Photographs.; Masonic orders; Travel photography--Oregon.; Oregon Zoo (Portland, Or.)
Oregon; Home and Family
Tintypes (prints); Photographs
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.
- Family History, Series A
  - Letters and emails, 2010 (Box-folder 1/1)
- Photographs, Series B
  - Travel and battleship (negatives only), 1915; undated (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Portraits, identified, ca. 1910 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Portraits and snapshots, unidentified, ca. 1910 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Tintype portraits, unidentified, ca. 1900-1910 (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Family groups, unidentified, ca. 1890 (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Unidentified locations, ca. 1900 (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Travel photographs
    - Montreal, Quebec, Canada, ca. 1900-1910 (Box-folder 1/8)
    - Louisiana Purchase Exposition, 1904 (Box-folder 1/9)
    - Oregon and Victoria, BC, ca. 1910 (Box-folder 2/1)
    - Auto trip album, northestern Oregon, with notes on letterhead, 1914 (Box-folder 2/2)
    - Album belonging to H. C. Weber, St. Helens, Astoria, “Keat family villa,” Gearhart (1912); Gearhart, Salem, Willamette River, Eugene, Victoria, B.C., Pendleton (1912) (Box-folder 2/3)
    - U.S. travel, general, ca. 1910-1920; undated (Box-folder 2/4)
  - Battleship Oregon in Portland, 1929; 1940 (Box-folder 2/5)
  - Album, loose pages: Columbus Day storm in Portland, 1962 (Box-folder 2/6)
  - Album, loose pages: Oregon Zoo, 1960 (Box-folder 2/7)
- Newspaper Clippings, Series C
  - Oregon Zoo, previously known as Washington Park Zoo, Portland, 1960-1961 (Box-folder 2/8)
- Books and Ephemera, Series D
  - Masonic Lodge, 1918-1950; undated (Box-folder 2/9)
  - Printed album, images of University of Oregon, property of Bertha Elizabeth Slater, 1895 (Box-folder 2/10)
  - Booklet and photo, Washington High School reunion, property of Bernice Weber Smith, 1994 (Box-folder 2/11)